American Revolution Collection
Connecticut Historical Society
American Revolution Collection
1776-1786
Connecticut Historical Society, Hartford, Connecticut
Connecticut Historical Society
5.5 linear feet (11 boxes)
Collection consists of records of the Council of Safety, whose function it was to handle the day to day affairs of Connecticut's wartime government; records of the Commissary department which was responsible for providing food and equipment for the soldiers; records of the Committee of Paytable which paid for supplies and services; payroll records of Col. Sheldon's Light Dragoons; the commissary and paymaster records of the Third Regiment, Connecticut Line; orderly books, journals and correspondence describing activities of Connecticut persons during the Revolution.
History
American colonists in the mid-eighteenth century felt that the economic policies of Great Britain were unfair and that they did not have a sufficient voice in making decisions regarding these policies. Colonial boycotts of British goods did sufficient damage to force the repeal of the Stamp Act in 1766 and the Townshend Acts in 1770. When Parliament punished Massachusetts for destroying thousands of pounds of tea in Boston Harbor, the organized groups that had introduced these boycotts rebelled. The colonists had not intended to wage a war and were totally unprepared to provide soldiers with the weapons, training, clothing and food needed.
Scope and Content
The collection has been organized into nine series: Records of the Council of Safety (1774-1783), Commissary Records (1774-1783), Pay Table Records (1774-1783), Colonel Sheldon's Light Dragoons (1770-1783), Third Regiment, Connecticut Line (1779-1780), Journals and Orderly Books (1775-1782), Account books (1775-1783), Naval affairs (1773-1789), and Correspondence (1774-1853).
Series I: The Records of the Council of Safety consists of muster rolls, returns, exemptions, substitutes, deserters, prisoners and soldiers missing in action.
Series II: The Commissary Records relate to the organization and deployment of supplies and ordnance for the military.
Series III: The Committee of the Pay Table was set up to authorize disbursements and examine and settle accounts for supplies and services needed for the Revolutionary War. It was succeeded by the office of the Comptroller in 1786. The series consists of accounts, returns and receipts concerning the payment of soldiers.
Series IV: Pay Table Records Payroll records of Colonel Sheldon's Light Dragoons are found in the fourth series.
Series V: The fifth series contains payroll and commissary records of the Third Regiment, Connecticut Line.
Series VI: Journals and Orderly books are arranged alphabetically by name. They describe the siege of Boston in 1775, the expedition against Canada in 1775, the campaign around New York in 1776 and 1777 and the Burgoyne campaign in 1777.
Series VII: Commissary and paymaster Account Books comprise the seventh series.
Series VIII: Naval Affairs series includes correspondence of Timothy Parker, commander of the frigate "Oliver Cromwell", Nathaniel Shaw, naval agent for Connecticut, John Deshon, agent and commissary at New London, Connecticut and records dealing with the conversion of merchant vessels to ships of war.
Series IX: Correspondence of Asa Waterman, commissary of purchases for the Continental Army, of Peter Colt, deputy quarter master general of the Eastern department and letters of other Connecticut persons describing their activities during the American Revolution.
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions on access to the collection.
Accruals
The collection is closed.
Subject Headings
Personal Names
Burgoyne, John, 1722-1792.; Billings, Sanford.; Boardman, Benjamin.; Brown, Obadiah.; Butler, Zebulon, 1731-1795.; Chapman, Samuel, 1729-1813.; Chapman, William.; Chester, John, 1749-1809.; Clark, Elihu.; Culver, David.; Curtis, Giles.; Douglass, John, 1734-1809.; Hart, John.; Hart, Timothy, 1731-.; Hempsted, John.; Hillyer, Andrew, 1743-1828.; Hooker, Roger.; Janes, Elijah, 1744-1826.; Morgan, Joseph, 1754-1829.; Pease, Calvin, 1757-.; Pierce, John.; Porter, Elijah.; Richards, Samuel.; Riley, Ashbel.; Shaw, Thomas, 1739-1795.; Stanton, William.; Sherman, Isaac.; Smith, David, 1747-1814.; Smith, Joel, 1748-1835.; Spencer, Joseph, 1714-1789.; Tracy, William.; Ware, Daniel.; Webb, Charles, 1724-1780.; Wyllys, Samuel.
Corporate Names
Connecticut Militia. 10th Regiment.; Oliver Cromwell (ship).
Subjects
Saratoga Campaign, 1777.
Geographic Names
United States History Revolution, 1775-1783 Registers, lists, etc.; United States History Revolution, 1775-1783 Supplies.; United States History Revolution, 1775-1783 Finance, commerce, confiscations, etc.; United States History Revolution, 1775-1783 Claims.; United States History Revolution, 1775-1783 Hospitals, charities, etc.; United States History Revolution, 1775-1789 Economic aspects.; United States History Revolution, 1775-1783 Sources.; United States History Revolution, 1775-1783 Regimental histories.; United States History Revolution, 1775-1783 Personal narratives.; United States History Revolution, 1775-1783 Naval operations.; United States History Revolution, 1775-1783 Prisoners and prisons.
Genre Forms
Holographs; holographs, signed; printed forms completed in manuscript.
Contents:
- I. Records of the Council of Safety
  - Muster Roll of Colonel Return Jonathan Meigs., 1779; (1 item) (Box 1, Folder A)
  - Muster Rolls of Captain Abel Pettibone., 1774; (3 items) (Box 1, Folder B)
  - Muster Rolls, 1775 - 1781; (18 items) (Box 1, Folder C)
  - Muster Rolls: Transcripts and photocopies., 1777-1782; (7 items) (Box 1, Folder D)
  - Military Exemptions., 1771-1777; (35 items) (Box 1, Folder E)
  - Substitutes, 1777-1781; (6 items) (Box 1, Folder F)
  - Deserters, 1781; (1 item) (Box 1, Folder G)
  - List of Men Killed at Fort Groton., 1781; (1 item) (Box 1, Folder H)
  - Miscellaneous, 1774-1781; (7 items) (Box 1, Folder I)
  - Returns for 1775., (1 item) (Box 1, Folder J)
  - Returns for 1776., (1 item) (Box 1, Folder K)
  - Returns: Prisoners and Soldiers Missing in Action., 1777; (2 items) (Box 1, Folder L)
  - Returns: Rhode Island Expedition., 1777; (1 item) (Box 1, Folder M)
  - Returns for 1777., (8 items) (Box 1, Folder N)
  - Returns: 4th Brigade Militia., 1778; (1 item) (Box 1, Folder O)
  - Returns for 1778., (8 items) (Box 1, Folder P)
  - Returns: Resolution by the General Assembly., 1779; (1 item) (Box 1, Folder Q)
  - Returns: 21st Regiment of Militia., 1779; (1 item) (Box 1, Folder R)
  - Returns for 1779., (3 items) (Box 1, Folder S)
  - Returns for 1780., (5 items) (Box 1, Folder T)
  - Returns: Recruits for the Continental Army, as reported by James Hyde, 1781., (5 items) (Box 1, Folder U)
  - Returns: 1781 and undated., [177? - 178?]; (16 items) (Box 1, Folder V)
  - Returns: Transcripts and Photocopies., 1781; (1 item) (Box 1, Folder W)
- II. Commissary Records
  - Clothing., 1775-1782; (42 items) (Box 1, Folder X)
  - Forage., 1777-1779; (4 items) (Box 1, Folder Y)
  - General Hospital, Hartford., 1778-1779; (6 items) (Box 1, Folder Z)
  - Ordnance., 1775-1782; (25 items) (Box 1, Folder AA)
  - Ordnance: Receipts for lead., 1777; (10 items) (Box 1, Folder BB)
  - Provision Returns from Robert Blair., 1782; (1 item) (Box 1, Folder CC)
  - Provision Returns from Elijah Hubbard., 1779-1781; (6 items) (Box 1, Folder DD)
  - Provision Returns from Elijah Lewis., 1776-1777; (1 item) (Box 1, Folder EE)
  - Provision Returns from James Robinson., 1781; (21 items) (Box 1, Folder FF)
  - Provision Returns from Asa Waterman., 1777; (51 items) (Box 1, Folder GG)
  - Return of Provisions Destroyed in a British Raid, 1777; (3 items) (Box 2, Folder A)
  - Provision Returns: Flour, 1775-1776; (31 items) (Box 2, Folder B)
  - Provision Returns: Survey of Grain Supply., 1779; (18 items) (Box 2, Folder C)
  - Provision Returns and Receipts (including records for the French Army)., 1773-1787; (61 items) (Box 2, Folder D)
- III. Pay Table Records
  - Training Accounts., 1774 - 1776; (6 items) (Box 2, Folder E)
  - Lexington Alarm (Includes statement of soldier who returned on foot)., 1775-1777; (57 items) (Box 2, Folder F)
  - Lexington Alarm,(continued)., 1775; (45 items) (Box 2, Folder G)
  - Lexington Alarm: Accounts of Captain James Clark, 1775; (10 items) (Box 2, Folder H)
  - Ticonderoga, 1777., (2 items) (Box 2, Folder I)
  - Bounties., 1777-1782; (5 items) (Box 2, Folder J)
  - Mileage Rolls., 1776-1777; (4 items) (Box 2, Folder K)
  - Pay rolls: Captain Elijah Babcock's Company, 1775-1776; (2 items) (Box 2, Folder L)
  - Pay rolls: Colonel Charles Burral's Regiment, 1776; (6 items) (Box 2, Folder M)
  - Pay rolls: Colonel John Douglas' Regiment, 1776-1777; (15 items) (Box 2, Folder N)
  - Pay rolls: Colonel J. Dugan's Regiment, 1776-1777; (7 items) (Box 2, Folder O)
  - Pay rolls: Colonel Samuel Elmore's Regiment, 1776; (6 items) (Box 2, Folder P)
  - Pay rolls: Colonel John Ely's Regiment, 1776; (1 item) (Box 2, Folder Q)
  - Pay rolls: Colonel James Livingston's Regiment, 1776-1777; (3 items) (Box 2, Folder R)
  - Pay rolls: Colonel Samuel McClellan's Regiment, 1777-1778; (2 items) (Box 2, Folder S)
  - Pay rolls: horse teams: conductors Broadhurst - Garvin, 1782; (9 items) (Box 2, Folder T)
  - Pay rolls: horse teams: conductors Holmes - McDonald, 1775-1782; (17 items) (Box 2, Folder U)
  - Pay rolls: horse teams: conductors Milton - Moore, 1782; (12 items) (Box 2, Folder V)
  - Pay rolls: horse teams: conductors Nichols - Pannill, 1782; (6 items) (Box 2, Folder W)
  - Pay rolls: horse teams: conductors Ray - Smith, (9 items) (Box 2, Folder X)
  - Pay rolls: General, 1776; (19 items) (Box 2, Folder Y)
  - Confiscated estates (includes statement that Continental Army soldiers were paid from the proceeds)., 1781-1792; (9 items) (Box 3, Folder A)
  - Accounts and Receipts (includes two from African -American soldiers)., 1775-1792; (43 items) (Box 3, Folder B)
  - Records: Monies Due., 1773-1784; (5 items) (Box 3, Folder C)
  - Comptrollers: Disability Certificates., 1783-1789; (2 items) (Box 3, Folder D)
  - Comptrollers: Claims and Settlements for Military Service, 1792-1852; (32 items) (Box 3, Folder E)
  - Troops Furnished by Each State and Claims Therefor., 1776-1783; (7 items) (Box 3, Folder F)
  - Selectman's Reports on Quotas and Soldiers' Families., 1775-1783; (6 items) (Box 3, Folder G)
- IV. Colonel Sheldon's Light Dragoons
  - Records of Paymasters E. Janes and W. Stanton., Feb. 1779 - Apr. 9, 1783; (49 items) (Box 4, Folder A)
  - Records of Paymasters E. Janes and W. Stanton., Apr. 10 - Jun. 5, 1783; (54 items) (Box 4, Folder B)
  - Records of Paymasters E. Janes and W. Stanton., Jun. 6 - Jun. 12, 1783; (71 items) (Box 4, Folder C)
  - Records of Paymasters E. Janes and W. Stanton., Jun. 13 - Aug. 5, 1783; (52 items) (Box 4, Folder D)
  - Records of Paymasters E. Janes and W. Stanton., Aug. 6 - Sep. 30, 1783; (56 items) (Box 4, Folder E)
  - Records of Paymasters E. Janes and W. Stanton., Oct. - Dec., 1783; (62 items) (Box 4, Folder F)
  - Records of Paymasters E. Janes and W. Stanton., Jan. - Mar., 1784; (57 items) (Box 4, Folder G)
  - Records of Paymasters E. Janes and W. Stanton., Apr. 1784 - Jul. 5, 1786; (52 items) (Box 4, Folder H)
  - Records of Paymasters E. Janes and W. Stanton., Jul. 5, 1786 - Jul. 30, 1787; (52 items) (Box 4, Folder I)
  - Records of Paymasters E. Janes and W. Stanton., Aug., 1787 - 1822 & undated; (30 items) (Box 4, Folder J)
  - Payroll., 1780-1783; (1 item) (Box 4, Folder K)
  - Other General Records, (16 items) (Box 4, Folder L)
- V. Third Regiment, Connecticut Line
  - Muster rolls: 1779 - 1780., (18 items) (Box 5, Folder A)
  - Pay Master's record book: 1779 - 1780., (1 item) (Box 5, Folder B)
  - Pay Master's records (includes information on sick, deceased and deserted)., 1779-1780; (42 items) (Box 5, Folder C)
  - Pay Master's records., 1779-1780; (11 items) (Box 5, Folder D)
  - Pay Master's records: substitutes., 1779; (1 item) (Box 5, Folder E)
  - Commissary records: arms., 1777-1779; (4 items) (Box 5, Folder F)
  - Commissary records: clothing., 1777; (9 items) (Box 5, Folder G)
  - Commissary records: clothing., 1778; (33 items) (Box 5, Folder H)
  - Commissary records: clothing., 1778; (14 items) (Box 5, Folder I)
  - Commissary records: clothing., 1779; (18 items) (Box 5, Folder J)
  - Commissary records: clothing., 1779; (20 items) (Box 5, Folder K)
  - Commissary records: clothing., 1779; (21 items) (Box 5, Folder L)
  - Commissary records: clothing., 1779; (48 items) (Box 5, Folder M)
  - Commissary records: clothing., 1780; (43 items) (Box 5, Folder N)
  - Commissary records: clothing., 1780; (57 items) (Box 5, Folder O)
  - Commissary records: provisions., 1779-1780; (75 items) (Box 5, Folder P)
  - Commission to Joshua king., 1779; (1 item) (Box 5, Folder Q)
- VI. Journals and Orderly Books
  - Sanford Billings: journal., 1776 (Box 6, Volume A)
  - Benjamin Boardman: journal., 1775 (Box 6, Volume B)
  - Oliver Boardman: journal., 1777 (Box 6, Volume C)
  - Obadiah Brown: journal (photoprinted copy)., 1776 (Box 6, Volume D)
  - Zebulon Butler: orderly book., 1782 (Box 6, Volume E)
  - Zebulon Butler: orderly book., 1782 (Box 6, Volume F)
  - Samuel Chapman: orderly book., 1782 (Box 6, Volume G)
  - William Chapman: journal., 1775 (Box 6, Volume H)
  - John Chester: orderly book., 1776 (Box 6, Volume I)
  - Elihu Clark: journal., 1775 (Box 6, Volume J)
  - Continental Regiments: orderly book., 1775 (Box 6, Volume K)
  - Continental Regiments: orderly book., 1776 (Box 6, Volume L)
  - David Culver: orderly book., 1778 (Box 6, Volume M)
  - Giles Curtis: orderly book., 1782 (Box 6, Volume N)
  - John Douglass: orderly book., 1776 (Box 6, Volume 0)
  - Moses Fargo: orderly book (transcription)., 1775 (Box 6A, Volume P)
  - Christopher French: orderly book., 1776 (Box 6A, Volume Q)
  - John Hart: orderly book., 178l (Box 6A, Volume R)
  - Timothy Hart: orderly book., 1780 (Box 6A, Volume S)
  - John Hempsted: orderly book., 1776 (Box 7, Volume A)
  - Andrew Hillyer: orderly book (typed transcription)., 1775 (Box 7, Volume B)
  - Roger Hooker: orderly book (typed transcription)., 1775 (Box 7, Volume C)
  - Roger Hooker: orderly book (photostat), 1775 (Box 7, Volume D)
  - Simeon Lyman: journal (manuscript excerpt), 1775 (Box 7, Volume E)
  - Joseph Morgan: orderly book., 1782 (Box 7, Volume F)
  - Nathaniel Morgan: journal., 1775 (Box 7, Volume G)
  - Calvin Pease: journal., 1775 (Box 7, Volume H)
  - John Pierce, Jr.: orderly book., 1777 (Box 7, Volume I)
  - Elijah Porter: journal (transcription)., 1780 (Box 7, Volume J)
  - Samuel Richards: orderly book., 1780 (Box 7, Volume K)
  - Ashbel Riley: orderly book., 1780 (Box 7, Volume L)
  - Isaac Sherman: orderly book., 1778 (Box 8, Volume A)
  - David Smith: orderly book., 1778 (Box 8, Volume B)
  - David Smith: orderly book., 1779 (Box 8, Volume C)
  - David Smith: orderly book., 1779 (Box 8, Volume D)
  - David Smith: orderly book., 1779-1780 (Box 8, Volume E)
  - David Smith: Orderly book., 1780 (Box 8, Volume F)
  - Joel Smith: orderly book., 1779 (Box 8, Volume G)
  - Joel Smith: orderly book., 1779-1780 (Box 8, Volume H)
  - Joseph Spencer: orderly book (bound with printed copy)., 1775 (Box 8, Volume I)
  - William Tracy: orderly book (photostat)., 1777 (Box 8, Volume J)
  - Benjamin Trumbull: journals., 1775-1777 (Box 9, Volume A)
  - John Trumbull: orderly book., 1776 (Box 9, Volume B)
  - J. Waller: orderly book., 1776-1777 (Box 9, Volume C)
  - J. Waller: orderly book., [177?] (Box 9, Volume D)
  - Daniel Ware: orderly book., 1777 (Box 9, Volume E)
  - Charles Webb: orderly book (typescript)., 1775-1776 (Box 9, Volume F)
  - Bayze Wells, orderly book., 1775-1777 (Box 9, Volume G)
  - Samuel Wyllys: orderly book, 1775-1776 (Box 9, Volume H)
  - Orders (Box 9, Volume I)
- VII. Account Books
  - Account Book., 1777-1779 (Box 9, Volume 1)
  - Assistant Commissary of Issues to General Glover's Brigade., 1778-1783 (Box 9, Volume 2)
  - Commissary., 1779-1781 (Box 9, Volume 3)
  - Commissary cash book., 1775-1780 (Box 9, Volume 4)
  - Commissary cash books, nos. 4-11., 1776-1777 (Box 9, Volume 5)
  - Commissary receipt book., 1782 (Box 9, Volume 6)
  - Commissary record book., 1777 (Box 9, Volume 7)
  - Commissary record book., 1782 (Box 9, Volume 8)
  - Commissary record book., 1783 (Box 9, Volume 9)
  - Commissary record book: deliveries, 1783 (Box 9, Volume 10)
  - Paymaster General records, part I., 1775-1778 (Box 9, Volume 11)
  - Paymaster General records, part II., 1775-1778 (Box 9, Volume 12)
  - Paymaster General records, part III., 1775-1778 (Box 9, Volume 13)
  - Paymaster General records, parts IV-V., 1775-1778 (Box 9, Volume 14)
  - Paymaster General: receipt books, parts I-III., 1775-1776 (Box 9, Volume 15)
  - Paymaster General: receipt books, 1776-1777 (Box 9, Volume 16)
  - Paymaster General: receipt books, parts I-III., 1777-1778 (Box 9, Volume 17)
- VIII. Naval Affairs
  - Correspondence of Timothy Parker., 1773-1781 (Box 10, Folder A)
  - Letters from Curtis Reed to his wife Sibbil Reed., 1779 (Box 10, Folder B)
  - Correspondence of Nathaniel Shaw., 1777 - Feb., 1779 (Box 10, Folder C)
  - Correspondence of Nathaniel Shaw., March - April, 1779 (Box 10, Folder D)
  - Correspondence of Nathaniel Shaw., May - June, 1779 (Box 10, Folder E)
  - Correspondence of Nathaniel Shaw and Thomas Leaming., 1779 (Box 10, Folder F)
  - Correspondence of Thomas Shaw and John Deshon., 1779 (Box 10, Folder G)
  - Letters to Thomas Shaw, Commissioner of Prisoners., 1779 (Box 10, Folder H)
  - Letters to Governor Jonathan Trumbull., 1781-1782 (Box 10, Folder I)
  - Letter from Joseph Trumbull., 1778 (Box 10, Folder J)
  - Records re Conversion of Merchant Vessels to Ships of War., 1780-1783 (Box 10, Folder K)
  - Records of the Armed Ship Oliver Cromwell., 1776-1778 and undated (Box 10, Folder L)
  - Letters (Transcripts, extracts, photocopies)., 1775- (Box 10, Folder M)
  - Letters (Transcripts, extracts, photocopies)., 1775- (Box 10, Folder N)
  - Letter of Marque against the Dutch., 1781 (Box 10, Folder O)
  - Records., 1774-1789 and undated (Box 10, Folder P)
- IX. Correspondence
  - Correspondence of Royal Flint., 1778-1779 (Box 10, Folder Q)
  - Letter from Matthew Graves to George Washington., 1776 (Box 10, Folder R)
  - Letter from John Hancock to Nathaniel Shaw., 1776 (Box 10, Folder S)
  - Letter (transcription) from Joshua King re. Major Andre., 1817 (Box 10, Folder T)
  - Correspondence of John Sullivan., 1778-1779 (Box 10, Folder U)
  - Correspondence of Asa Waterman., 1777-1778 (Box 10, Folder V)
  - Letters from Peter Colt to Asa Waterman., 1778 (Box 10, Folder W)
  - Letters from Thomas Lloyd Halsey to Asa Waterman., 1778 (Box 10, Folder X)
  - Letters (Originals)., 1774 (Box 11, Folder A)
  - Letters (Originals)., 1775 (Box 11, Folder B)
  - Letters (Originals)., 1776 (Box 11, Folder C)
  - Letters (Originals)., 1777 (Box 11, Folder D)
  - Letters (Originals)., 1778-1779 (Box 11, Folder E)
  - Letters (Originals)., 1780-1781 (Box 11, Folder F)
  - Letters (Originals)., 1782-1790 (Box 11, Folder G)
  - Letters (Originals)., 1791-1824 (Box 11, Folder H)
  - Letters (Originals)., 1825-1852 (Box 11, Folder I)
  - Letters (transcriptions) from Roger Welles., 1780-1783 (Box 11, Folder J)
  - Abstracts of letters., 1775-1778 (Box 11, Folder K)
  - Maps. (Box 11, Folder L)
  - Documents., 1765-1853 (Box 11, Folder M)
  - Documents: Call for Relief of Boston, 1774 (Box 11, Folder N)
  - Documents, undated (Box 11, Folder O)
  - Documents: (Transcripts, extracts, photocopies) (Box 11, Folder P)
  - Miscellaneous. (Box 11, Folder Q)
  - Publications based on collection. (Box 11, Folder R)